Guide to the Gary Soto Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gary Soto papers
1977-2003
YCAL MSS 640
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.43
(15 boxes) + 1 portfolio and 1 motion picture film
The Gary Soto Papers contain writings, audiovisual material, and other papers that document the professional life of Gary Soto.
Soto, Gary, 1952-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from various sources, 1999-2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 13, 15, and 17 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 16 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Gary Soto (1952- )
Gary Soto, Mexican-American author, poet, and filmmaker. Soto was born on April 12, 1952, and was raised in Fresno, California.
Scope and Contents
The Gary Soto Papers contain writings, audiovisual material, and other papers that document the professional life of Gary Soto.
Arrangement
Organized into eight groupings: I. February 1999 Acquisition. II. April 1999 Acquisition. III. January 2000 Acquisition. IV. June 2000 Acquisition. V. January 2001 Acquisition. VI. November 2001 Acquisition. VII. November 2003 Acquisition. VIII. November 2004 Acquisition.
American literature -- Mexican American authors -- 20th Century; Mexican American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Motion pictures (visual works); Sound recordings; Video recordings; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Soto, Gary, 1952-
- February 1999 Acquisition, 1990-1998, undated; 1; (1 box) + 1 portfolio
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased from Arte Americas on the Adele Gutman Nathan Theatrical Collection Fund, 1999.
  Scope and Contents
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 604
  Contains correspondence, scripts, printed material, sound and video recordings, and a musical score by or relating to Soto.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 17 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for more information.
  - The Bike
    - Financial records, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Publicity, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, contracts, and releases, 1992 (Box 1)
    - The Bike, TRT 12:30, 1991; ycalmss640_0002; 1; 00:12:46 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002102338259)
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Dog Cruise off Ensenada, script, undated (Box 1)
  - Flaco, script and agreement, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Kung-Fu Grandpas, treatments, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Los Screamies, script, undated (Box 1)
  - Nerdlandia, scripts, 1996-1998; 5 (Box 1)
  - Nerdlandia, musical score, undated (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - Novio Boy
    - Scripts, 1995, undated; 2 (Box 1)
    - Production records, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Publicity, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Novio Boy, teleplay by Gary Soto, undated; ycalmss640_0003; 1; 00:27:29 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002102338267)
    - Novio Boy, Amigos Unidos Club of Fresno Pacific University presents, undated; ycalmss640_0004; 1; 01:24:26 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002102338275)
  - The Pool Party
    - Script, undated (Box 1)
    - The Pool Party, undated; ycalmss640_0005; 1; 00:29:31 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002102338283)
  - The Skirt, script and other material, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Taking Sides, script, undated (Box 1)
  - Up Stream with Pilar and Diko, script, undated (Box 1)
  - Hunger soundtrack, sound recordings, undated; (1 reel-to-reel tape and 1 audiocassette)
    - Hunger soundtrack, undated; 1; 00:14:39; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 15, Item barcode 39002091243890)
    - Hunger, undated; 1; 00:14:33; Kodachrome stock with 1984 and 1985 Kodak date codes. (Box 15, Item barcode 39002091243908)
- April 1999 Acquisition, 1980-1999, undated; 2; 1.21; (2 boxes)
  Purchased from Gary Soto on the Sinclair Lewis Fund, 1999.
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 611
  Contains writing drafts by Soto, proofs for illustrations by Robert Casilla with a related letter, and letters from Christopher Buckley to Gary Soto.
  - Poem drafts, undated (Box 3)
    The Story on This Street, Making Up Time, and Hitch-hiking
  - Correspondence, 1989 January 1 (Box 3)
  - Interview with Gary Soto by Christopher Buckley, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Prose complement for "The Geography of Home: An Anthology", 1998 (Box 3)
  - Big Bushy Mustache or The Mustache, script, 1994, 1997; 2 (Box 3)
  - Boys at Work
    - Letter from editor Michelle Poploff, 1994 June 3 (Box 3)
    - Near final draft, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    - Draft marked "Final", 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Chato and the Mexican Mystery: Chato and the Mexican Mystery, draft, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Chato and the Mexican Mystery: Chato Celebrates the Day of the Dead, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Chato Throws a Pachanga: Chato and the Party Animals, draft, 1996-1997; 2 (Box 3)
  - Chato Throws a Pachanga, untitled mock-ups of the illustrations, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Crazy Weekend, near final draft, undated (Box 3)
  - Mi Carro: Mi Carro, draft, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Mi Carro: Mi Carro es Muy Firme, draft, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Mi Carro: Mi Carrito, draft, 1998; 2 (Box 3)
  - Off and Running
    - Draft, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Final draft, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Compositor's proof, second pass, 1995 November 21 (Box 3)
    - Various compositor's pages, 1996 (Box 3)
  - The Old Man and His Door, near final draft, undated (Box 3)
  - Petty Crimes, typescript draft, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Petty Crimes, author's galleys, 1997 November 3 (Box 3)
  - The Pool Party, final, 1993 February 12 (Box 3)
  - The Pool Party, printer's blues, 1993 March 15 (Box 3)
  - Sand Bites, drafts, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Summer on Wheels, letter from editor Ann Reir, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Summer on Wheels, near final draft, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Soto from Christopher Buckley, 1980-1999, undated; 12 (Box 4)
- January 2000 Acquisition, 1973-1999, undated; 3; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Purchased from Arte Americas on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2001.
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 647
  Contains correspondence, writing drafts, printed material and a CD recording by or relating to Gary Soto. Includes correspondence, book reviews and notes relating to Gary Soto's tenure case at the University of California.
  - Greenfield Review, "NCAE Ethnic Writers Workshop-Stevens Point", 1973 (Box 5)
  - University of California at Berkeley, tenure review material
    - Book reviews, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Three journals with reviews of Soto's books, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Living Up the Street, typescript draft, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Comments on tenure case, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Taking Sides, copyedited and edited typescript, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Contributors to Ploughshares edit by Soto, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - Familiar Song, typescript, undated (Box 5)
  - Buried Onions, typescript edited, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Self Portraits, published book, undated (Box 5)
  - Buried Onion, 1995, 1997; 2 (Box 6)
  - Too Many Tamales, undated (Box 6)
  - Whiting Foundation correspondence, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Nickel and Dime
    - The Literary Life, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Untimely Passing of the Radio, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Ars Poetica, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Locations, "Teaching English," radio play written and narrated by Soto, undated; (1 compact disc) (Box 6)
    Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Deck of Soto trading cards, unopened, undated (Box 6)
  - Ploughshares, Spring 1995 (Box 6)
- June 2000 Acquisition, undated; 4; 1; (1 box)
  Purchased from P. Scott Brown on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2000.
  Former call number: Uncat ZA File 410
  - Baseball in April: typescript, early draft, with revisions. Includes: The Karate Kid, Undue Worry, Marble, The Barbie Doll, Mother and Daughter, The Gullible Kid, Two Dreamers, First Love, The Guitar and the Lost Dog, The Talent Show, Detective Mike, The New Year and Tell the Truth., undated (Box 7)
- January 2001 Acquisition, 1977-1978, undated; 5; 1; (1 box)
  Purchased from Arte Americas on the Thornton Wilder Memorial Fund, 2001.
  Formerly Uncat MSS 96
  Arrangement
  Contains writing drafts by Soto.
  - Elements of San Joaquin, review by Juan Rodriguez: typescript, 1977 (Box 8)
  - The Tale of Sunlight: typescript, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Small Faces, 10 (Box 8)
  - Jessie de la Cruz (Box 8)
  - Nickel and Dime, 12 (Box 8)
  - Various drafts, 3 (Box 8)
  - Computer Media
    - GARY SOTO, 2001-ycal-0118-b-0001; 1 (Box 16)
      Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
- November 2001 Acquisition, 1998-2001, undated; 6; 1.05; (3 boxes)
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 210
  - Nerdlandia, copy edited typescript, undated (Box 9)
  - Jessie de la Cruz, 1998-2000; 14 (Box 9)
    Includes corrected typescript drafts, photographs, interview typescripts, research notes, cover art, notebooks, and correspondence
  - The Effect of Knut Hamsun of a Fresno Boy, typescript, and "master" first galleys, 1999-2000; 2 (Box 10)
  - Poetry Lover, corrected draft and book design software printout, 2000-2001; 4 (Box 10)
  - Poetry Lover, blue line proofs and various material, 2001, undated; 3 (Box 11)
- November 2003 Acquisition, 1977-1997, undated; 7; 0.51; (2 box) + 1 film
  Purchased from the California Rural Legal Assistance, Inc. on the Sinclair Lewis Fund, 2003.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 576
  - Ronnie and Joey, typescript, 1977 (Box 12)
  - Tall Dog, typescript corrected, 1988 (Box 12)
  - The Untimely Passing of the Clock Radio, 1997; 4 (Box 12)
  - Novio Boy, producer Gary Soto, undated; ycalmss640_0001; 1; 00:35:19 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002102300267)
  - The Bike, undated; (1 16mm motion picture film)
    - The Bike, 16mm motion picture film, undated (Box 13 (Cold Storage))
- November 2004 Acquisition, 1995-2003; 8; 0.21; (1 box)
  Purchased from Gary Soto on the Stanton Francis Kennedy Fund, 2004.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 729
  - El maullido de la gata, 1995 (Box 14)
  - No place like home, 2002 (Box 14)
  - Cesar Chavez: a hero for everyone, advance reader's copy, 2002-2003; 6 (Box 14)
  - Chato goes cruisin', various revised drafts and correspondence, 2001-2003; 5 (Box 14)